foreign
[Music]
on my previous video we locked into
Boyle's Law Charles law and gay lussac's
law
with this one the whole idea behind it
is that it's looking at pressure volume
and temperature meaning that moles are
going to be kept constant we're not
adding any more gas we're just changing
the conditions that they are under is
all about change so going from an
initial to a final value so how do we
kind of combine all these three laws
together how exactly
does that work well this is where I'm
going to get a little Matthew on you how
are we going to combine them well the
idea is if I take the original formulas
we have so if I first start with Boyle's
Law
what we are going to do is we're going
to fold in the other formulas so meaning
that I'm going to take Boyle's Law
multiply it by Charles law
and then multiply it by galusax law so
let's do the first one so if I take
um Boyle's Law multiply in Charles law
what we are going to do is we're going
to bring it in on both sides
so when we do that you can see that okay
these are going to get multiplied
now if that's to happen we're going to
combine like terms so as you can see the
V ones are the same
so when this gets brought down what
we're going to have is P1
V1 squared
T1 and then it's a very similar story on
the other side we'll have P2 V2 squared
because they're like terms they get
multiplied so these are getting
multiplied
and then T2
next we're going to fold in the next law
which is galusax law
so when we have that we're going to
multiply that to
I'm going to take both of them I'm on
both sides
we're going to once again put those in
parentheses
and we're going to combine like terms
again notice how the pressures are the
same
and so are the temperatures so what are
we going to end up getting
is we'll have P1 squared V1 is still
squared
T1 squared
is equal to P2 squared V2 squared
and T2 squared oh man this is a oh
interesting problem so how do we
simplify this how do we get rid of
squares well we use a square root so
when we do that we'll square root both
sides and this leads to our combined gas
law
which will be P1 V1
over T1 is equal to P2 V2
over T2
this is our formula so this combines all
of them together into one giant formula
so this is the combined gas law it is a
powerful equation that allows us to be
able to incorporate three of our four
variables so pressure volume temperature
moles are constant so they are not in
this equation we don't worry about them
it's all about change
so what kind of problems would you see
with something involving this much
change
so if I look at this first example
if you have a 10 liter balloon at
standard temperature and pressure
okay so this goes back to the first
video of what the heck is standard
temperature and pressure
so whenever you have STP that's defining
a specific condition so we had our
volume it mentioned at the beginning
STP tells you what the pressure and
temperature are for an ideal gas for how
can we do simple calculations so one is
the pressure at sea level which is one
atmosphere
and then the temperature for the Kelvin
scale how to convert it from Celsius is
273 so that's the temperature that's
used
now it says the pressure is increased
okay so we're taking that pressure that
is increasing so P2 is going to two
atmospheres
and that I got from right here in that
equation then we also have that the
temperature increased to 300 Kelvin so
T2
also increase and that equals
300 Kelvin
now the question is what is the
balloon's new volume so the one thing we
don't know is we have no idea what the
volume is so let's take our equation
that we defined earlier and what we're
going to do is we're going to get V2 by
itself it's easier to rearrange the
problem first than to just start
plugging numbers and that's usually when
the most calculator errors occur so
rearrange first it's doing just
multiplication division to rearrange it
always looks scary but I promise you
practice it it will get easier the more
you do it
so we're trying to get V2 by itself so
how can we
do that is we can multiply by the
inverted equation of P2 and T2 so how
can we look at this equation
so being that V2 let's move things
around
is what we're interested in
the way we can kind of write that is
instead like this so P2 and T2
times our times volume right
so in order to cancel these well we just
got to multiply it by its inverse
so what that causes is this to cancel
this
and
temperature to cancel temperature so we
multiply both sides
and what we will get is T2 P2 and we
will get our new equation that we can
use for volume and you can write this
down if you're a little nervous about
um deriving things it's something that
you can that you can use
so we have our new equation
and what we're going to do is we're
going to plug in all of our values into
this
so what it's going to end up being
is we'll take our P1 which was 1
atmosphere
times that by V1 which was 10 liters
and then times that by T2 which was 300K
that's our numerator or what's on top
and then P2 and T2 were two atmospheres
times oh I just realized I have T2 twice
so and then it's going to be Times by T1
sorry about those no so there was a
little typo there
so that should be T1
that'd be times 270
3 Kelvin
all right and that's on bottom
so we'll take one times ten times three
hundred solve for that
then divide by 2 times 273. now when we
get this we'll get our volume which in
this case you will get a volume of 5.49
liters
as your answer and that's how you use
the combined gas law now let's try
another one because this is one I think
that there's a there are several ways to
sell there's many variables so how else
could you solve use it well for this one
let's say if I have the volume of a
container is increased from 100
milliliters to 425 milliliters
so what it's telling you is is we have
two volumes here and there's the keyword
two
so when we are looking at this right we
have a V1 and a V2
so let's break those down we have an
initial volume of 100 milliliters
and that's increasing to a final volume
of 425 milliliters
and it says that causes the pressure of
the gas to increase
from 500 Milli millimeters of mercury to
1200 millimeters of mercury so we have
also a P1
and a P2
all right so we'll write those down for
ourselves
and then we also says that it starts at
an initial temperature of 300K so this
is a helpful method for ourselves
identify all the important pieces of
information so that way you don't have
this big word problem staring you at the
face when you're going through this go
through it slowly identify it make it
simple for yourself
so when you're going through this we are
noticing all the important pieces
and we can see that okay what is it
asking me to do well you can identify
you have five out of six variables the
missing piece is what is the final
temperature so we want to know what is
T2 and all this right T2 is our missing
piece
so let's try to look at our formula
and see can we get
T2 by itself easily now one thing you
might have saw in my previous video was
oh T2 is on the denominator is there an
easy way to get this by itself
this is where we'll invert it we're
going to flip
so we're gonna flip it while I'm using
highlighter there but we're going to
flip this then we're going to flip the
script
so when we flip it what that's going to
become
is T1 over P1 V1
is equal to T2 P2 V2
this allows for T2 to be by itself a
little bit faster so you are taking the
inverse when you do this
so what we're going to do is multiply
both sides by p2v2
and what that's going to do is get that
T2 by itself those cancel out and we'll
have our new formula which will be P2 V2
T1
P1 V1 is all equal to T2
all right we have a lot of variables to
plug in here so that's what we're going
to do we're going to plug all those in
sorry I kind of zoomed out here for a
second but I want to see all the
variables
so pressure 2
was 1200 millimeters of mercury
Volume 2 was 425 milliliters
T1 was 300K
and that's all going to be divided by P1
and V1 so your original values so that's
500 millimeters of mercury
times a hundred milliliters okay so
those are all of our values when we are
looking at these and we are going to
solve for the top so be 1200 times 425
times 300 solve and divide by 500 times
100 in parentheses so when you get that
you're going to get a massive
temperature you get a value of 30 60
Kelvin as our temperature so it says
when all those are increasing because we
have in this problem that volume
increases and pressure increases they're
typically inverse of one another that
does not commonly happen
so because of all that well it's
something that the temperature needs to
compensate so the temperature skyrockets
as a result
okay our last major law for now for in
terms of change so our last law in terms
of changing
Avogadro's Law is all about avocados
right so Avogadro or avocados law as we
kind of like the joke around here about
that is all about volume and moles so
and it's this really simple one let's
say if you take a balloon and it's empty
right so it has zero moles of gas in it
you blow into it it inflates the moles
of gas increase you blow into it more it
gets bigger the moles of gas increases
so with this one it's all about how much
are you blowing up a balloon how much
how much bigger are you so as you add
moles it's going to be increasing in
size meaning volume increases if you
suck out the balloon it decreases in
size moles are also decreasing so if we
want to do a problem with this it's a
it's a simple one to end on is if I have
six liters of gas
so that's our initial
volume
and its contains
0.847 moles of gas
and that and what will happen What will
be the new amount sorry what would be
the new amount of gas so we want to know
what N2 is
if the quantity is decreased to
3.80
liters okay
so
what exactly are we looking at when that
happens well we're going to be plugging
it into our equation so when this one we
had our equation was V1 N1 is equal to
V2
N2
so we need to get N2 by itself so once
again we can do the same trick from
before right we could move some things
around we could also arguably use the
other equation I had up here which was
um V1 and which was V1 n
two
is equal to V2 N1 it's rearranging it so
we could do a couple different things so
when we rearrange that equation to
figure out what is N2
what we need to do is divide both sides
by V1 so it's going to be V2 N1 divide
by V1
so when we have that
what that's going to look like
is V2
N1 divide by V1
okay so if we plug in our values
we have
3.80 liters
multiplied by moles which is
0.847 moles
and that's going to be divide by 6
liters and this is something that's
predictable right as we look across we
can see volume is decreasing so what
should happen to the number of moles
they should also be decreasing so when
we solve for this what you're going to
be getting as a final answer is that
you're going to have 0.424
moles of gas that's going to be forming
and that's our final answer for this
problem is that the gases are going to
be decreasing so the volume is
decreasing moles are decreasing
I hope that this video helped this is
going through the last equation
regarding change there are still more
gas laws to come involving the ideal gas
law which will have a probably at least
one or two videos going through those so
please like And subscribe to have more
content to be able to help you pass your
chemistry class and for you to do the
best possible I hope to see you again in
the future and this is Dr Dan and it's
been a pleasure to help you with
chemistry I'll see you all later bye
foreign